How's it going everyone? In this video,
we are going to cover what is a candle 2
closure. Now, within my fractal model, I
have two candle closure types, a candle
2 and a candle 3 closure. So, let's get
into this video that covers candle 2
closures. So, the first thing you have
to understand is the difference between
a continuation closure and a reversal
closure. So this is in a bearish
scenario. We have price trending lower.
Are we anticipating price to continue or
to reverse? Here you can see we sweep
out the previous candle's low. And where
do we close? We close below it. When
price closes below the previous candle's
low, I can anticipate a continuation
lower. However, with a reversal closure,
that is when we sweep out the previous
candle's low, but we don't close below
it. We close back inside the previous
candle's range or above this candle's
low, and that is a reversal closure. And
I can anticipate price to go in the
other direction. Now, a candle 2 closure
is focused on when we have a reversal
closure or we sweep out that previous
candle's high or low and then close back
inside the range. So, taking a look at
this diagram here, you can see we have a
reversal closure or a candle 2 closure
where in the bullish scenario here,
price sweeps out the previous candle's
low and then closes back above that
candle's low, signifying that price has
reversed in candle 2 or this low here.
In a bearish scenario, we have price
sweeping out the previous candle's high
and then closing back below it, showing
that it has reversed in this candle too
here. Now, it's important to note that
we want this to occur at a higher time
frame key level. If you just look for
every pattern that has a sweep and a
closure back in, that is unlikely to
work. You want to define this with bias
and a higher time frame point of
interest, which I use fair value gaps
and highs and lows. So, once we have
this closure, we can then anticipate
candle 3 to have a continuation. And you
may want to check out my video on
trading candle three. But following this
closure, we're looking for price to
expand higher or in the bearish scenario
for price to expand lower. Now, with a
closure outside the previous candle's
range, so you can see candle 3 here
closing over candle 2, is that a
reversal closure or a continuation
closure? That is a continuation closure.
So, we can anticipate price to expand
higher as well in candle 4. And the same
in the bearish scenario here. We close
below candle 2's low. So, we can
anticipate it to continue lower in
candle four as well. And there you can
see candle four gets an expansion which
finishes off this candle 2 closure and
this swing point. So, just to review, we
have a candle 2 closure, closing back
above the low of candle 1, allowing
candle 3 to expand. Candle 3 closes
strong or over candle 2's high, which
allows candle 4 to expand as well. And
in the bearish scenario, we have candle
2 closing back below candle 1's high.
Candle three closing very strong below
candle 2's low and then candle four
continuation. Now once again it's really
important that we combine this with a
higher time frame key level or a point
of interest being a high low or a fair
value gap. Now let's say we want to
blend this with my equilibrium video.
That's where we can go ahead and mark
out these areas we expect the wick to
form in the higher time frame candles.
So with a candle two closure here, if I
have a large wick, I'm going to want to
watch the upper half of that wick to see
if candle 3 forms its wick in respect to
that. If it doesn't respect the 0.5,
then it's likely to fail and a swing
point is unlikely to form. And then with
candle 3, we can do the same as we have
a strong closure. I'll mark out the
entire candle's range, 50% of that,
looking for a continuation. If you don't
know what I'm talking about here, I'll
link the two videos in the description
below of using wicks and using EQ. Now,
let's hop into Trading View and go over
a few examples of spotting candle 2
closures. Here we are in Trading View,
and the best way to identify candle 2
closures is to just practice finding
them on the chart. So, what you'll want
to do is just go find swing points. So,
find any point in which the market made
a turn and go ahead and mark them all
out and then we'll go back through and
determine which one of these are a
candle 2 closure. So, here you can see
we have quite a few marked out. Let's
see which ones are actually candle two
closures. To have a candle two closure,
we need price to take out its previous
candle's high and then close back below
it in a bearish scenario or take out its
previous candle's low and close back
above it in a bullish scenario. So here
you can see price sweeps out its
previous candle's high and then closes
back below it having a candle 2 closure
looking for a candle three continuation
lower. Now looking at this swing point
here, we have price sweeping out the
previous candle's low, closing back
above it. So that is a candle 2 closure.
I could look for price to trade higher.
I'm just going to repeat this looking
for those reversal patterns. So, you can
see sweeps out the previous high, closes
back below it. You can see it trading
lower. And we'll go ahead and just mark
all of these out. So far, you can see
all of these are candle 2 closures. But
as we look at these swing points over
here, this is not a candle to closure as
price never closed back below its
previous candle's high. And the same
right here, this is not a candle to
closure as price did not close back
above its previous candle's low. So,
those were two that I would remove right
away. Now, if you noticed, these are all
candle 2 closures, but do they all occur
at a point of interest? And that is what
I'm going to want to mark out. So,
taking a look here, we have a high that
we sweep out. That is a point of
interest. So, this is valid to look
lower the next day. Here we have a point
of interest, sweeping out a low. So,
it's valid for this to look higher the
next day. And having to zoom out, you
can go to the monthly chart and see we
took out a previous high from quite long
ago, but we use that as a point of
interest here for this candle to
closure. But one thing I will also add
is ideally we want candle 2 to have a
reversal to set up a candle 3
continuation. But here you can see price
formed a shallow wick and had an
expansion in candle 2 as well. That does
not set up the best conditions for
candle 3 as what can occur after an
expansion a new phase of price. But
nonetheless this is valid here. You can
see do we have a point of interest? No,
we fail to sweep out this low. So this
is not one we would look for here. Right
here we reach into this fair value gap.
So, it is a valid candle to closure to
look lower. Right here, you can see we
sweep out all these previous lows. So,
it's valid for this to look higher. And
then this one here, we fail to take out
this high. So, it is not valid, right?
Because I do not have that point of
interest. And I need a point of interest
to frame a candle closure. Now, what do
we notice about this? We do form a
protected swing. So, I am not looking
for price to return to this level. If
it's going to trade higher, that's when
I can actually use the opposing candles
as a point of interest. and why this one
would remain valid. It's more advanced,
but it is a valid one cuz I can use
these opposing candles as the point of
interest. And then right here on this
most recent one, we have a sweep of this
previous high, which provides the point
of interest for this candle to closure
and for price to trade lower today. So
once again, just to review, the best way
to find this is to practice on the daily
chart or a higher time frame. And you
want to find those candle closures
first, then see if they have a point of
interest, and then that gives you bias,
right? So looking back at this, I could
be bearish this day, bullish this day,
bearish this day. You can see it doesn't
set up well because this already
expanded right after this high. Bearish
this day, bullish this day, bullish this
day, bearish this day. And that's the
easiest way to get bias is just finding
those candle to closures on the daily
chart. So if we remove all these
drawings, we'll go into today. We have a
sweep of a previous high, a candle to
closure. Now, if you followed my model
or my playbook, you know the next thing
we're going to do is drop down to our
aligned time frame. So, here we have a
daily chart. We're going to drop down to
the hourly chart. So, going into the
replay here, you can see we have this
candle to closure on the daily time
frame as shown by these higher time
frame candles. Let it finish out. And
right there, we open a new candle. So,
by marking out this candle 2 closure,
how do we confirm this on a lower time
frame or get a validation of this candle
2 closure? We look for a change in the
state of delivery. We're going to find
the high. Find the series of candles
that made that high, which is
essentially here. Mark that out. And
then now we can anticipate price to do
what? To continue lower as long as it
remains in respect to the previous
candle's range. You can see here's a
consolidation. It's hard to trust that
high. So as long as price doesn't trade
up into these highs, right, it is valid
to look for it to continue lower. And
that's why we use the EQ. I want to see
price respect this area here. So, as we
let this play out, you can see we do go
take out a point of interest. And what
do we notice now? It's a fractal
concept. So, if we zoom in, what do we
have? We have a candle to closure at a
point of interest on the hourly chart.
Not only can this provide a bias for
this next candle to trade lower on a
lower time frame, but we can anticipate
this to be where the high a day forms.
And then what can we look for?
Continuations out of this. So, let's see
what happens. Right there you can see we
do what? We reach up into a point of
interest and we have what? A candle to
closure. So what does that tell us? If
we are going to continue and leave this
high, we should anticipate a
continuation here to trade lower. And
you can see we do get that continuation
lower. And that's where we're at today
right now. So just to review, this is
how you align time frames. It's a
fractal concept. Here we have a candle
to closure. And I'm just going to
confirm that using the align time
frames. So, if I'm on the daily, I'm
going to use the hourly for a change in
the state of delivery. If I'm on the
hourly, I will use the 5minute. I'm just
going to use those time frame pairings.
And if I want to make this really
simple, this is where I will add in my
indicator that marks out that candle to
closure for me. Marks out that change in
the state of delivery and that EQ in
that area I'm looking for a continuation
lower as well as those liquidity
targets. So, let's get into a few more
examples. But the main thing I want you
to take away from this video is how to
spot a candle 2 closure and practice
finding them. I have videos on candle 3
and how to trade them following a candle
2 reversal. So if you want more info on
that, check out that video. But as you
can see here, it is a fractal concept
and works on all time frames. So here we
are on micro Bitcoin futures. And what
do we notice about this monthly candle
here? We have price sweeping out a point
of interest or a previous high and then
forming what? a candle to closure by
closing back inside the previous candle.
On the daily time frame here, we have a
high. We have a close through the series
of candles that made that high. So, what
do we have? We have a valid monthly and
daily fractal model that says we want to
trade to these lows. So, getting into
this candle three or for this
continuation, we can use this on the
daily time frame fractally. We have a
point of interest. We have what? Another
candle 2 closure. And what could we do
here is we could refine this down to the
hourly. And you can see how it's
fractal. We can go from the monthly to
the daily to the hourly. But going to
the hourly here, what do we have? Let's
replay to here so we can watch it play
out. We have a daily swing point or a
daily candle to closure forming with
SMT. Do we have a change in the state of
delivery? We do cuz we find the high,
the series of candles that made it. And
then we could be looking for a
continuation lower. And that is where
the T-spot comes in where I'm looking to
sell in these boxes here. So, as we can
see, we retrace up and what do we form
right at this high into this point of
interest? We have a candle 2 closure and
this gets a continuation lower. And what
are we saying about candle 3? If candle
3 closes below candle 2's low, we can
look for candle 4 to continue lower as
well. And that is why another T-spot is
being printed out. So, into this next
day, we see price trade higher. And what
do we notice about this high here? We
also have a candle to closure and we
have equal lows below and more equal
lows below. So could be looking for this
to trade lower and we do. And then since
we close below the low, we could be
looking for a continuation lower. Now
the one thing I'll say once you get into
candle five and six, that's where you
can get caught in a new phase of price.
So you have to be a bit more careful.
But there we are today trading lower.
And this is just a fractal concept. So
let's go to something like the 4hour
chart. And you can see, do we have a
candle 2 closure here? No, we do not.
That is a candle 3 closure, which we'll
talk about in a future video. But let's
let this continue. We displace down. We
retrace. Do we have a candle 2 closure?
We do. We displace. We retrace. Candle
to closure. Here we have a little gap
from the overnight. And what do we do?
We continue lower. What are we forming
right now? A candle 2 closure. So what I
wanted to explain just in this video is
a lot of times a candle 2 closure will
mark a turning point in the market and
it's very critical to understand what
they look like and how they can be used.
So for instance here let's say I wanted
to trade this lower. Then I could use
the 15-minute chart to look for a
15-minute fractal model based off this
4hour time frame. We can just repeat
this across numerous different time
frames. So you can see we have a candle
to closure confirmed with the change in
the state of delivery and I can look for
this area to respect to trade lower. So
I hope you enjoyed this video. If you
did, please consider liking and
subscribing and I'll see you guys in the
next video going over candle 3.